Helen Rachel Williams Papers, 1888-1910
Smith College Archives
Helen Rachel Williams Papers
1888-1910
Williams, Helen Rachel, 1871-1957
RG 80 UUID:41adf773-d699-4ac6-8b0d-e891750808dd
2 boxes (0.8 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Smith College Class of 1892. Contains correspondence and photographs.
Helen Rachel Williams was born in Canton, Massachusetts on August 6, 1871. She was the daughter of W.J. Williams and Mira G. Draper Williams. Her father was a manufacturer. Helen was educated at the Berkeley School and was a self-professed Unitarian. She entered Smith College in 1888, and received her B.A. degree in 1892. During college, she lived at Washburn House and, not surprisingly, most of her friends and correspondents lived in that house during college as well. After graduation, Williams moved back to Canton, Massachusetts and became a teacher in the Canton school system, teaching from 1895-1912. She never married and died January 24, 1957.
The collection contains primarily letters written to Helen Williams from her Smith College friends. Her and her friends write during college and afterward, telling each other of their lives and activities. Other correspondents include several male friends and colleagues, as well as her siblings. The collection also contains two photographs of the room Helen occupied in Washburn House, probably during the 1891-1892 academic year.
An index of letters is avaliable.
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
The materials in the Helen Rachel Williams Papers, which form part of 80. Student Files, were donated to the College Archives by Pat Jennings. They were donated in the name of Nicole Jennings, Class of 2004. The Jennings family is not related to Helen Rachel Williams. Pat Jennings purchased this collection of letters from a dealer and subsequently donated them to the Smith College Archives.
- Correspondence (Box 1471.1)
- American Society for Psychical Research 1907 (Box 1471.1, Folder 1)
- Association of Collegiate Alumnae, Boston Branch 1892-1894 (Box 1471.1, Folder 2)
- Barry, Florence (1893) 1891-1894 (Box 1471.1, Folder 3)
- Barton, Blake undated (Box 1471.1, Folder 4)
- Bourland, Caroline "Carrie" "Psyche" (1893) (Box 1471.1, Folder 5)
  See also: 42. Bourland, Caroline 1891-1904
- Burnham, Gertrude 1895-1898 (Box 1471.1, Folder 6)
- Darling, Frances (1893) 1892-1898 (Box 1471.1, Folder 7)
- DeMerritte, Edwin-of the Berkeley School, Boston, MA 1888-1889 (Box 1471.1, Folder 8)
- Dickerson, May Florence 1892-1895 (Box 1471.1, Folder 9)
- Dole, Mary "Mollie" Mitchell (ex-1893) 1892-1904 (Box 1471.1, Folder 10)
- Dunbar, Olivia Howard (1894) 1892-1903, undated (Box 1471.1, Folder 11)
- Easton, Marie Louise 1899, 1901 (Box 1471.1, Folder 12)
- Granger, Edith (1891) 1890 (Box 1471.1, Folder 13)
- Haven, Katherine (1892) 1894-1907 (Box 1471.1, Folder 14)
- Hendrie, Jennie Frances (ex-1892) 1890-1892 (Box 1471.1, Folder 15)
- Howard, Susan A. undated (Box 1471.1, Folder 16)
- Jepson, Harry S. 1894 (Box 1471.1, Folder 17)
- Landon, Grace (1893) 1889 (Box 1471.1, Folder 18)
- Landon, Mary (1893) 1889-1890 (Box 1471.1, Folder 19)
- Lane, Grace (1893) 1892-1894 (Box 1471.1, Folder 20)
- Lathrop, Clara S. 1891 (Box 1471.1, Folder 21)
- Love, Grace (1893) 1892 (Box 1471.1, Folder 22)
- Lowry, Ethel C. 1896 (Box 1471.1, Folder 23)
- Mansfield, Christine (1892) 1892-1893 (Box 1471.1, Folder 24)
- Mills, Harriet C. (1893) 1892 (Box 1471.1, Folder 25)
- Morse, Herbert A. 1893 (Box 1471.1, Folder 26)
- Murkland, Charlotte "Lottie" (1893) 1891-1898 (Box 1471.1, Folder 27)
- Noyes, Bertha L. (1894) 1893 (Box 1471.1, Folder 28)
- Paul, Florence Helen (1891) 1898, 1901 (Box 1471.1, Folder 29)
- Peterson, Helen (ex. 1893) ca.1893 (Box 1471.1, Folder 30)
- Procter, Adeline W. (1893) 1892-1896 (Box 1471.1, Folder 31)
- Reed, Frank H. 1906-1907 (Box 1471.1, Folder 32)
- Scovill, Florence May (1893) (Box 1471.1, Folder 33)
  See also: Dole, Mary Mitchell 1894-1904, n.d.
- Scovill, William L. 1903-1904 (Box 1471.1, Folder 34)
- Smith, Amy Gertrude 1897-1898 (Box 1471.1, Folder 35)
- Timmerman, Charlotte (ex-1893) 1890 (Box 1471.1, Folder 36)
- Waldo, Grace (ex-1892) (Box 1471.1, Folder 37)
  See also: Wyman, Evelyn 1892-1902
- Watt, Edith 1890 (Box 1471.1, Folder 38)
- White, Marion Ballantyne (ex-1892) 1889-1904 (Box 1471.2, Folder 1)
- Williams, Anne (sister) 1889 (Box 1471.2, Folder 2)
- Williams, Roger (brother) 1899 (Box 1471.2, Folder 3)
- Wyatt, Mabel Preston (1893) 1891-1893 (Box 1471.2, Folder 4)
- Wyatt, Mabel Preston (1893) 1894-1903, undated (Box 1471.2, Folder 5)
- Wyman, Evelyn (ex-1894) 1891-1893 (Box 1471.2, Folder 6)
- Unidentified individuals 1891-1910 (Box 1471.2, Folder 7)
- Invitations 1895-1905, undated (Box 1471.2, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous 1888, undated (Box 1471.2, Folder 9)
- Photographs ca.1892 (Box 1471.2, Folder 10)